A Guide to the Carl Archacki Papers, 1986-2004, n.d.
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Carl Archacki Papers 1986-2004, n.d.
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M349
1 linear ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated to Special Collections and Archives by Carl Archacki in June 2005.
Biographical Information
Carl Archacki, born January 1957 in Meadville, Pennsylvania, was raised in Cambridge Springs, Pennsylvania, and is the youngest and only son (with three older sisters) of Carl Frank Archacki and Helen Mamrak Archacki. As an infant, Archacki was baptized into the Catholic Church and has remained devout since. Archacki has served various outreach roles in his younger years, specifically with the Catholic Youth Association (CYA) in the Erie Diocese. In his outreach efforts, Archacki learned from his parents' model-as they were both "incredible examples in their communities and church throughout their lives."
In May 1979, Archacki graduated from Ashland University, Ashland, Ohio, with a Bachelor of Arts in Communication and directly entered the broadcast sales arena with the CBS affiliate, WSEE in Erie, Pennsylvania. In 1986, Archacki moved to Richmond, Virginia, to begin a sales career with then WXEX, which became WRIC (Richmond's local ABC affiliate) in 1990. Archacki has been with WRIC for more than twenty years and is currently the Regional Sales Manager. While in Richmond, Archacki became involved with Dignity / Integrity, a religious support group for gay / lesbian Catholics and Episcopalians, and would serve as both Vice-President and President of the local Richmond chapter.
In the 1990s, Archacki became involved with the Sexual Minorities Commission of the Catholic Diocese of Richmond. The commission, an official Catholic outreach support group that ministered to the spiritual and pastoral needs of gay / lesbian Christians and their families, operated for twenty-five years under the support of Bishop Walter Sullivan. It was dissolved in 2004 by the Richmond Diocese. Archacki served as chair of the commission for six years and helped organize and carry out many retreats and workshops throughout the Richmond Diocese. He also helped establish the National Association of Catholic Diocesan Lesbian and Gay Ministries and served on its national board.
For more than twenty years, Archacki has been an active parishioner of the Cathedral of the Sacred Heart, where he has been involved with various ministries, including: the Rite of Christian Initiation of Adults (RCIA), Social Ministry Program, Pastoral Council, Communications Committee, and Communion Minister. Archacki's role in activism outreach activities has also spread into the secular environment and has included work with Equality Virginia, the Human Rights Campaign, the Richmond Ad Club, the Richmond Aids Business Council, the Richmond City Democratic Party, and the Richmond Gay Pride Coalition.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1986-2004, n.d., of Carl Archacki, a Richmond activist for equal rights and an advocate for gay and lesbian support groups, principally consisting of clippings, memorandums, photographs, and leaflets concerning his work as a member of the Sexual Minorities Commission of the Catholic Diocese of Richmond, Dignity / Integrity, the Human Rights Campaign, and the Richmond Pride Coalition.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series:
Series I: Sexual Minorities Commission Files
Series II: Photographs
Series III: Publications
Contents List
- Sexual Minorities Commission Files, 1990-2004, n.d. (Box 1)
  Arranged alphabetically. Contains mostly clippings, announcements, and leaflets addressing homosexuality in the Catholic Church. Clippings concern the first official Mass for gays and lesbians in Richmond held at the Cathedral of the Sacred Heart. Leaflets include announcements on the annual gay Mass and programs from the Liturgy and literature on Catholicism and homosexuality.
  - 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - n.d., 1990-2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Photographs, 1987-1998 (Box 1)
  Arranged chronologically. Contains photographs from various equal rights and gay / lesbian pride events in Richmond, VA and Washington DC, including Diversity / Integrity meetings, benefits, and banquets; three historic March on Washington demonstrations to end homophobic discrimination and strengthen AIDS awareness, 1988, 1993, and 1996; the Human Rights Campaign Fund, and the Sexual Minorities Commission.
  - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1992 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1992 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1993 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1993 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1996 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1996 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1996 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1996 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1997 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1998 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Publications, n.d., 1986-1997 (Boxes 2-3)
  Arranged alphabetically. Consists of clippings, magazines and programs that document various equal rights and gay / lesbian pride events, including, the 1987 and 1993 March on Washington for gay / lesbian rights and AIDS awareness; Richmond Lesbian / Gay Pride Festivals; Dignity / Integrity events; and the Richmond Lesbian and Gay Pride Coalition.
  - 1987, 1992, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1986-1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1993 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1993 (Box 3)
  - n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)